{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This thinker claimed that human motivation was divided between eros and thanatos, or the life and death drives. This man divided the title constructs into manifest and latent content in his The Interpretation of Dreams. This thinker divided the unconscious into the ego, superego, and the id. Controversially claiming that young men develop an Oedipal [[ED- ih-\"pull\"]] complex, for ten points, which Austrian psychologist is considered the father of psychoanalysis?",
      "answer": "Sigmund Freud or Sigismund Schlomo Freud"
    },
    {
      "question": "An island in this nation owned by naval officer William Owen was named by him Campobello in an effort to gain favor with the sitting royal governor, Lord William Campbell. The former mining town of Uranium City and many oil sands drilling sites are on the shore of this country's Lake Athabasca [[AH-thah-BAH-skah]]. In this nation, the SS Mont Blanc's collision with the SS Imo led to the deadly \"Halifax Explosion\" during the First World War. For ten points, name this North American country whose major cities include Ottawa and Montreal.",
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "question": "The story of this opera was adapted for a 1998 musical of the same name with music by Elton John. An original \"potpourri\" overture was written for this opera, though it was cut from the 1871 premiere in Cairo. At the end of this opera, the title Ethiopian princess dies in the arms of her lover Radamès [[rah-dah-MESS]], while priests sing hymns to Ptah. For ten points, name this four-act opera by Giuseppe Verdi about a romantic tragedy in the Old Kingdom of Egypt.",
      "answer": "Aida"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 1942 movie musical titled for this song follows the life of George M. Cohan. The Marquis de Lafayette’s band played this song as the British surrendered at Yorktown. In this song, the title character and his father “went down to Camp” with Captain Gooding and saw “men and boys / As thick as hasty pudding.” For ten points, name this song about an American who “stuck a feather in his cap / And called it macaroni.”",
      "answer": [
        "“Yankee Doodle”",
        "\"Yankee Doodle Dandy\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1982, two laid-off Chrysler workers killed a man of this ethnic group in Highland Park, Michigan due to their anger at their company being outcompeted by the Japanese auto industry. This people group, who were killed en masse in the Rock Springs Massacre, experienced California's discriminatory Anti-Coolie Act. An 1882 \"Exclusion Act\" was passed to limit immigration by, for ten points, what Asian ethnic group, many of whom immigrated during the late Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty?",
      "answer": "Chinese-Americans"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two students from this institution began the St. Scholastica Day Riot after being served poor quality wine. Rhodes Scholars are given full-rides to this university, which initially grew after Henry II banned his countrymen from attending the University of Paris. Following the 1209 lynching of two students from this institution, many scholars left to found its rival, Cambridge. For the point, name this university, the oldest in the English- speaking world.",
      "answer": [
        "University of Oxford",
        "Oxford University"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these people was convicted in the case Tuckiar v The King after killing a police constable who assaulted the women of his tribe in Arnhem's Land. Turn-of-the- century laws in New South Wales and the Northern Territory allowed for the removal of the children of these people, collectively known as the Stolen Generations. In 1985, ownership of the site Uluru was given back to, for ten points, what indigenous people of Australia?",
      "answer": "Aboriginal Australians or Aborigines"
    },
    {
      "question": "American explorer Gene Savoy proved that this site and the legendary capital of Manco Yupanqui [[yoo-PAHN-kee]] Vilcabamba were distinct locales. A sun dial served as the centerpiece of this estate's Temple of Inti. This site, whose name translates to \"old peak\" in Quechua [[KEH-chwah]], likely served as the private estate of the Sapa Pachacuti. Hiram Bingham discovered, for ten points, what Incan citadel in the Andes of modern Peru?",
      "answer": "Machu Picchu"
    },
    {
      "question": "A \"Cantata\" named for this river was written to commemorate a heroic last stand by fishermen near its Hukou [[HOO-KOO]] Waterfall. With Hou Ji [[HOH-JEE]], the semi- mythical Emperor Yu the Great stopped this river from flooding by using self-expanding soil called Xirang [[ZHEE-RAHNG]]. The Sui [[SWEE]] Dynasty began the construction of the Grand Canal, connecting this river and the Yangtze River. For the point, name this \"Mother River\" of China, named for the color of its muddy water.",
      "answer": "Yellow River or Huáng hé ]"
    },
    {
      "question": "A mayor in this nation, Arturas Zuokas [[zoo-OH-kuss]], fought illegal parking in his city by crushing a car with an armored vehicle in 2011. This nation's language was preserved through the 19th-century \"Book Smuggling\" movement after Tsarist Russia banned its use. This modern state merged with a southern neighbor in the Union of Lublin, and it joined Estonia and Latvia in the anti-Soviet Singing Revolution. For ten points, name this Baltic state that formed a historical Commonwealth with Poland.",
      "answer": "Republic of Lithuania"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In his writing, Alexis de Tocqueville [[TOKE-vil]] called this practice \"alien\" to the United States, and it first began in the Confederacy in 1862. This practice led to the phrase \"A rich man's war and a poor man's fight.\" A massive 1863 riot broke out in New York City following an attempt to do this action to provide troops for the Civil War. For ten points, name this often unpopular practice of selecting people to serve in the military.",
        "answer": [
          "Draft",
          "Conscription"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A district court in Texas ruled in 2019 that male-only conscription was unconstitutional as it breached the equal protection clause of this Constitutional amendment.",
        "answer": "Fourteenth Amendment"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Lorentz transformation was confirmed by tests of this theory, including the Ives-Stilwell Experiment and the Kennedy-Thorndike Experiment. This theory's development introduced terms into physics such as spacetime and time dilation and helped scientists predict gravitational waves and black holes. For ten points, give this shared name of two interrelated theories by Albert Einstein, divided into \"general\" and \"special\" types, that applies to all physical phenomena in the absence of gravity.",
        "answer": [
          "Relativity",
          "Special Relativity",
          "General Relativity"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Though Einstein developed the theories of Relativity and several other groundbreaking discoveries, his 1921 citation for this major award only specifically mentioned his explanation of the Photoelectric Effect.",
        "answer": "Nobel Prize in Physics"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ganymede, the cup-bearer to Zeus, was the son of this city's founder. This city in Dardania was the site of the Palladium, and its king, Laomedon [[lay-AH-meh-don]], was killed after refusing to give a herd of magical horses to Herakles. Years later, this city was sacked thanks to the trickery of Odysseus, leading to the death of its last king, Priam [[PRY- am]]. Lying near the River Scamander, for ten points, what Anatolian city-state was the subject of a ten-year war fought over a woman named Helen?",
        "answer": [
          "Troy",
          "Troia",
          "or Truva",
          "Ilium",
          "Ilion",
          "or Ilios",
          "Wilusa",
          "or Truwisa"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Trojan War commenced because Paris abducted Helen from Greece, despite her being the wife of this powerful king of Sparta, the younger brother of Agamemnon.",
        "answer": "Menelaus ] or Menelaos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Transfer of footballers within this entity was the subject of the 1995 Bosman ruling. This entity is derived from an earlier \"Coal and Steel Community\" and was formally established by the 1992 Maastricht Treaty. In 2016, the United Kingdom voted in a referendum to leave this body, an act known as \"Brexit.\" For ten points, name this political and economic association of countries from the namesake continent.",
        "answer": "European Union or EU"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The United Kingdom is so far the only state to leave the EU. Many states have made overtures toward joining, however, including this Yugoslav successor state that agreed to change its name in 2019 to avoid conflict with its southern neighbor Greece.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of North Macedonia",
          "Macedonia",
          "Republika Severna Makedonija",
          "or Republika e Maqedonisë së Veriut"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the urging of Muhammad Ali, this man publicly denounced the Vietnam War in a speech delivered at the Riverside Church in New York City. During this man’s controversial “Poor People’s Campaign,” he went to the Mason Temple to deliver an address entitled “I’ve Been to the Mountaintop.” For ten points, name this first president of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference who delivered a speech on the steps of the Lincoln Memorial, declaring, “I Have a Dream.”",
        "answer": [
          "Martin Luther King Jr.",
          "MLK"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The \"I Have a Dream\" speech was delivered at the 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom, which was organized by A. Philip Randolph and this other major Civil Rights leader who was forced to work behind the scenes for most of his career due to his homosexuality.",
        "answer": "Bayard Rustin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This dynasty established hegemony after Emperor Tang won the Battle of Mingtiao [[MING-TYAO]] during the first \"Noble Revolution\" in East Asian history. This dynasty made its capital the city of Yin, near modern Anyang. During this dynasty, mystics began using turtle shells, or \"oracle bones,\" for divination. Following the Battle of Muye [[MOO-YUH]], the Zhou [[ZHOH]] overthrew, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty, the first with extensive archaeological records?",
        "answer": [
          "Shang Dynasty or Shāngcháo",
          "Yin Dynasty",
          "Yīndài before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Shang succeeded what semi-legendary dynasty founded by Yu the Great, the first traditional dynasty in Chinese historiography?",
        "answer": "Xia ] Dynasty or Xiàcháo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Cassius Dio reported that four of these people were wrongfully executed in a trial brought about by Caracalla on charges of crimen incesti [[KRIH-men in-KEH-stee]]. Emperor Elagabalus [[eh-lah-GAH-bah-lus]] caused controversy after marrying Aquilia Severa, one of these people. The mother of Romulus and Remus, Rhea Silvia, legendarily served as one of these priestesses. For ten points, name these \"Virgin\" priestesses of Rome dedicated to the goddess of the hearth.",
        "answer": [
          "Vestal Virgins",
          "Vestals",
          "or Vestālēs",
          "Priestess of Vesta"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Vestal Virgins were appointed by what official head of the Roman faith, a title later held by the Emperor.",
        "answer": "Pontifex Maximus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Early 20th century observers believed this building in the U.S. would collapse by itself, having become known as \"Burnham's Folly\" before construction. This building served as a hub of young publishers as the MacMillan Publishing company rented all 21 stories of this building by the mid 1950s. A contemporary reporter of the New York Tribune called this building \"A stingy piece of pie/the greatest inanimate troublemaker in New York.\" For ten points, name this triangular building which names a neighborhood in Manhattan.",
        "answer": [
          "Flatiron Building",
          "Flatiron District"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Flatiron Building was initially named for this \"Father of the Modern Skyscraper,\" whose construction company built the Lincoln Memorial and the New York Times Building.",
        "answer": "George Fuller"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Era of Good Feelings",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Era of Good Feelings from 1817 to 1825, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. president who was in office for most of the era.",
          "answer": "James Monroe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secretary of State who later defeated Andrew Jackson in a so-called \"Corrupt Bargain,\" ending the period.",
          "answer": "John Quincy Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "Early U.S. political party which collapsed following the Hartford Convention of 1814-15.",
          "answer": "Federalist Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kentucky politician and architect of the Compromise of 1820.",
          "answer": "Henry Clay"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Free\" state in New England admitted along with Missouri during the Compromise of 1820.",
          "answer": "Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Party that dominated U.S. politics during the period.",
          "answer": "Democratic-Republican Party or Jeffersonian Republican Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "1819 court case which concerned Maryland's attempt to tax the Second Bank of the United States.",
          "answer": "McCulloch v. Maryland"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York-born vice president during the era who spent much of his time away from Washington due to his poor health.",
          "answer": "Daniel D. Tompkins"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Age of Vikings",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Vikings, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Viking-settled region of northern France ruled by William the Conqueror.",
          "answer": "Normandy or Normanz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer who landed in modern Newfoundland in a place he called Vinland.",
          "answer": "Leif Erikson"
        },
        {
          "question": "General term for their raiding vessels, with Drakkar and Skeid [[SKEED]] varieties.",
          "answer": "Longships"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire using an elite infantry made predominantly of Vikings known as the Varangian Guard.",
          "answer": [
            "Byzantine Empire",
            "Eastern Roman Empire"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Norse king whose death at Stamford Bridge against Harold Godwinson left only two claimants to the English crown.",
          "answer": "Harald Hadrada or Harald III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alphabet they used to write Old Norse, often found on namesake \"Stones.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Runes or Runestones",
            "Runic Script"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Danish prince and king of England who created the North Sea Empire following the death of Sven Forkbeard.",
          "answer": "Cnut the Great or Canute the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "Englishman and scholar in the court of Charlemagne who recounted the first major Viking raid at the Abbey of Lindisfarne.",
          "answer": "Alcuin ] of York"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Syrian Civil War",
      "prompt": "Concerning the 21st century civil war in Syria, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "So-called \"caliphate\" which controlled much of Eastern Syria in the mid-2010s.",
          "answer": "ISIL"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. president who first called for strategic airstrikes in Syria in 2014.",
          "answer": "Barack Obama or Barack Hussein Obama II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Family of Ba'ath politicians including Hafez and Bashar, who presided over the government forces during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "al-Assad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nearby state whose IDF-led Operation Good Neighbor was an attempt to bring medical and humanitarian aid.",
          "answer": "State of Israel or Medinat Yisra'el"
        },
        {
          "question": "Turkish president who committed ground forces to the war in the mid-2010s.",
          "answer": "Recep Tayyip Erdoğan ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Syrian city whose Great Mosque was levelled following a four year-long battle.",
          "answer": "Aleppo or Halab"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lebanese militant faction and political party which sent both ground forces and convoys of weapons.",
          "answer": "Hezbollah or Ḥizbu 'llāh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurdish militia first formed during the Rojava campaign who are seen as terrorists by Turkey.",
          "answer": "People's Defense Units"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, unpledged electors from Alabama and Mississippi cast votes for Harry Byrd in opposition to the Democrats' move away from segregation, though the Democrats won anyway. For this election, that party nominated their second (20 pts)",
        "Catholic since 1928, choosing a Massachusetts senator who later died at the hands of Lee Harvey Oswald. The first televised presidential debates (10 pts)",
        "occurred during, for ten points, what election year in which Richard Nixon was defeated by John F. Kennedy?"
      ],
      "answer": "1960 United States Presidential Election"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The poor reception of an epic poem titled for this group led to the expulsion of Apollonius [[ah-poh-LOH-nee-us]] from the isle of Rhodes. At the request of King Pelias [[peh-LEE-ahs]], this group travelled to the homeland of Medea in (20 pts)",
        "the historical Kingdom of Colchis [[KOHL-kiss]]. The warrior who slayed the Minotaur, Theseus, was a member of this group, alongside (10 pts)",
        "Meleager and Orpheus. For ten points, name this group led by Jason who set sail to find the Golden Fleece."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Argonauts",
        "Argonautai",
        "Sailors of the Argo and equivalents",
        "Argonautica"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the late 18th century, this U.S. state created a system of five rotating capitals including East Greenwich [[GREHN-\"itch\"]] and South Kingston. During King Philip's War, the Great Swamp Fight occurred in this state, resulting in the mass enslavement of the (20 pts)",
        "Narragansett [[nair-ah-GAN-set]] people. This state was first settled by expelled Puritan minister Roger Williams. The colony of Providence Plantations was (10 pts)",
        "in, for the point, what modern New England state?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "State of Rhode Island",
        "its former name, until 2020, the State of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A Christian from this city named Anselm proposed the first ontological argument in his work Proslogion [[proh-SLOH-gee-on]]. Henry the Young King unknowingly ordered the 1170 execution (20 pts)",
        "of a church official from this city. Following the reforms of King Henry VIII [[the eighth]], the spiritual leader of Anglicanism is the archbishop of this city. Thomas à Becket served (10 pts)",
        "as the archbishop of, for ten points, what English city which names a set of Middle English Tales?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Canterbury",
        "Anselm of Canterbury",
        "Archbishop of Canterbury",
        "the Canterbury Tales"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This type of government was established following the successive overthrow of Hippias [[HIP-ee-us]] and the Spartan-favoring oligarchy of Isagoras [[iss- ah-GOH- russ]] in favor of Cleisthenes's [[KLYS-thin-eez-is]] reforms. This (20 pts)",
        "government style, for which Solon laid the foundations, included a punishment called ostracism, and was available to all citizens, though that excluded women and (10 pts)",
        "slaves. For ten points, name this isonomic government style that was adopted by ancient Athens, in which citizens governed themselves directly."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Athenian Democracy",
        "Demokratia",
        "Democratic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who advocated for the \"Five Races under One Union\" policy, incorporated his own Methodist beliefs into his \"New Life Movement.\" This man perpetrated the April 12th Purge of Communists (20 pts)",
        "and other workers led by Zhou Enlai [[ZHOH EN-\"LIE\"]]. This man's National Revolutionary Party formed the United Front with Mao's Red Army to (10 pts)",
        "defend against the Japanese. For ten points, name this \"Generalissimo\" of Nationalist China who fled to Taiwan in the 1940s."
      ],
      "answer": "Chiang Kai-shek"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Albert Einstein proved this statement using dissection without rearrangement, and James A. Garfield proved this statement using a trapezoid. For a Cartesian coordinate plane, the (20 pts)",
        "Euclidean distance formula can be derived from this statement. A Babylonian tablet called Plimpton 322 is the oldest known record of (10 pts)",
        "\"triples\" derived from this theorem that include examples such as (3,4,5) and (5,12,13). For ten points, what is this formula stated as \"A squared plus B squared equals C squared,\" named from a Greek philosopher?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Pythagorean theorem or Pythagoras's theorem",
        "Pythagorean triples",
        "\"equation\" in place of \"theorem\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In this year, England returned all continental possessions to the French, save Calais [[kah-LAY]], in the Peace of Étaples [[eh-TAHPL]]. The Jewish people of Spain were expelled or forced to convert in the Alhambra Decree (*) of this year, passed by Ferdinand and Isabella. In this year, the settlement of \"La Navidad\" was founded after the ship Santa Maria ran aground on Hispaniola. Christopher Columbus unintentionally (*) \"discovered\" the New World in, for ten points, what 15th century year?"
      ],
      "answer": "1492"
    }
  ]
}